I like to think of intents as envelopes
each one includes who, or in this case, which component you want it
delivered to. And there's room for a small amount of data to be delivered,
packaged as extras.
Primitive tuples that will be available to the application
component that ultimately receives and opens this intent. So an
explicit intent, explicitly specifies the name of the recipient, as
you can see on this envelope. Implicit intents are a
lot more interesting. Here, we don't specify the name of
the class. We don't even know what it is. So,
how do we indicate which activity to launch? Well, you
know those stories you sometimes hear about letters with fake
addresses like these that somehow still find their way to the intended
recipient? Well the intent resolution system on Android, works the same way.
Finding an activity, capable of performing an action
you specify on the associated data. So, rather than
specifying the name of a class, you indicate
an action you'd like an activity to perform, and
on what data that action should be performed.
Like this, where we want to address an activity
that's capable of viewing a website. And because intents
can cross through application boundaries, the activity that started,
may not be part of your app. So,
you can include functionality like this, browsing websites or
making phone calls or choosing a contact from your address book. All
from within your app, without you having to implement any of it yourself.
You don't even need to know about the app
that will ultimately service your request. You can find
details of some of the intents supported by native
apps in Common Intents page of the Android developer site.